John Gay Collection 1916-2002 LCP2002/001
Liberian Collections
John Gay Collection
1916-2002
Liberian Collections
Gay, John
LCP2002/001
12 cubic feet 12 records cartons
John Gay is a former professor and current scholar of Liberian and African studies. He began his career as a missionary for the Episcopal Church, teaching at Cuttington College in Liberia. John also had a number of fellowships that allowed him to develop his research and publish several works covering the civil war conflicts, culture, and social issues in Liberia. Though retired, John continues to have an active role in Liberian studies and currently serves on the Advisory Committee of the International Institute for Justice and Development. This collection contains his research, student publications, and other scholarly works.
Access Restrictions
Closed for research.
Biographical Note
John Gay is considered to be an expert on the subect of the Westernization of traditional societies. A priest, professor and scholar, Gay often writes about the civil war conflicts in Liberia and the clash between Westernization and traditional culture in his novels, articles and non-fiction works, His works include:
Long Day's Anger
Red Dust on the Green Leaves
The Brightening Shadow
Africa: A Dream Deferred
Liberia's Choices and Regional Stability
Intelligence in Action: A Study of Agruculture in Rural Liberia
The New Mathematics and an Old Culture: A Study of Learnign among the Kpelle of Liberia
The Rev. Dr. Gay served as an Episcopal missionary with his wife, The Rev. Dr. Judy Gay, in Liberia from 1958-1974. Gay and his wife continued their missionary work in Lesotho until he took an early retirement in 2001. In Lesotho he worked with the Sechaba Consultants on social and economic analysis, as well as various agricultural projects.
Gay began his missionary work in Africa at Cuttington College (now Cuttington University) located in Suacoco, Liberia, serving periodically from 1958-1965, 1966-1968, and 1970-1973. For those years he was Chairperson of the Social Science division and also Dean of Instruction from 1958-1960. Along with teaching, Gay also supervised student research projects, worked within the community, and conducted his own research. During a few of his years away from Cuttington, Gay had fellowships at Stanford University, 1965-1966, and Cambridge University, 1975-1976, and again in 1986. Gay took that time to study how new ideas in theology and social and economic development relate, as well as write up his research from in Liberia.
Gay later taught sociology and African studies at the National University of Lesotho. For two of those years Gay taught as a Fulbright Lecturer. He also voluntarily taught at the Anglican theological seminaries in Lesotho and South Africa.
After retirement, Gay became involved with the Episcopal Divinity School and Boston University, organizing seminary tours in Africa and administering contextual theology consultation at the Episcopal Divinity School.
Gay continues his support in current research done at Sechaba Consultants in Cambridge and in several visits completed from 2002-2005 to Lesotho, South Africa and Namibia. Because of his expertise, he now serves on the Advisory Committee of the International Institute for Justice and Development (IIJD).
Arrangement
The collection consists of seven series, which are divided into subseries. The series are as follows:
Agriculture
Culture
Economy
Education
Government
Linguistics
Publications
Scope and Content Note
The materials in the John Gay Collection consist of personal papers, publications, newspaper clippings, journals and magazines, interviews, and maps.
Specifically, the Agriculture series contains histories, interviews, names of plant varieities, reports, publications, and farming & land information.
The Culture series contains extensive field notes and papers documenting every facet of Liberian culture, including folklore and social structures. The series also contains the following: hand drawn maps, family histories, interviews, photographs of people and artwork, music, board game rules, myths, and religious information.
The Economy series contains industry case studies, company information, censuses, papers on trade, development, and slave trade.
The Education series contains curriculum information, papers on education development & reform, professional organization information, literacy projects, and papers & reports on problems in the educational systems of Liberia.
The Government series consists of papers on settlers, past presidents, government practices, foreign policy, and civil conflicts. Also included are articles, clippings, reports, maps and information on Liberian geography, interviews & papers on political systems, transcripts & reports on legal cases & trials, agendas, programs, and letters.
The Linguistics series contains Kpelle classifcation papers and field notes & research on the Kpelle language. Proverbs and information on other languages such as Loma & Liberian English are also included.
The Publications series contains scholarly works such as dissertations and theses, essays, official reports, poems, language & educational workbooks, journals, newspapers, magazines, and newsletters.
Separated Materials
All audio materials have been removed from collection and stored elsewhere for better storage and preservation.
Acquisition Information
Gift from Gay Family.
Copyright Transferred
Copyright interests for this collection have been transferred to the Trustees of Indiana University. For more information, contact the Indiana University Liberian Collections
Balama (Liberia); Liberia; Lofa County (Liberia); Liberia -- History -- 20th Century; Gay, John; D'Azevedo, Warren L.; Hayden, Tom; Holsoe, Svend E.; Tolbert, William R., Jr., 1913-1980; Tubman, William V. S., 1895-1971; Welmers, William Everett, 1916-1988; Cuttington College and Divinity School; Friends of Liberia (Organization); LAMCO; Liberia. Department of Education; Liberia. Ministry of Agriculture; Liberia. Ministry of Education; Liberia Watch for Human Rights; Liberian Research Association; National Teachers' Association of Liberia; Unesco; University of Liberia
- Agriculture 1964-2002 (Box 1)
  - Livestock
    - Sheep Dissection, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Agriculture in Liberia Reference Sources, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Conservation/Preservation, undated, 1964 - 1974 (Box 1)
    - Development, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Forestry, undated (Box 1)
    - History, undated (Box 1)
  - Rice Farming
    - Expansion, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Production, undated, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Survey, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Swamp Rice Cultivation, 1967 - 2002 (Box 1)
  - Types & Methods
    - 4-H Club, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Cash-Crops, undated, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Cooperatives, 1969 - 1973 (Box 1)
    - Free Association, undated, 1973 - 1974 (Box 1)
    - Kissi Farming, undated (Box 1)
    - Land, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Problem Methods, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Rubber, undated, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Smallholder Farming, 1967 - 1974 (Box 1)
    - Subsistence Farming, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Tenure Systems, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Traditional Farming, 1968 (Box 1)
- Culture 1916 - 2001
  - Anthropology
    - Fieldnotes - Bellman, 1967 - 1968 (Box 1)
    - Fieldwork, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Law & Personality, undated, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Customs
    - Bandi Folklore, undated, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Burial, 1967 - 1969 (Box 1)
    - Cultural Patterns undated, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Folktales, 1968 - 1972 (Box 1)
    - Friendship, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Kinship, 1966 - 1969 (Box 1)
    - Marriage, undated, 1963 - 1980 (Box 1)
    - Secrecy, undated (Box 1)
    - Secret Societies, undated, 1916 - 1972 (Box 1)
    - Social Organization, undated (Box 1)
    - Social Structures, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Trust, undated (Box 1)
  - Fine Arts
    - African Music, undated, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Art, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Hinterland Mythology, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Kayapo Myth, undated (Box 1)
    - Kpelle Music, 1972 - 1973 (Box 1)
    - The Legend of Chief Kortuma undated (Box 1)
    - The Life and Death of a Young Girl undated (Box 1)
    - Mammy Water, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Music Guides, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    - Plays, Stories, undated (Box 2)
    - Poetry, undated (Box 2)
    - Sankawulo Autobiography,, undated, 1965 - 1966 (Box 2)
    - Traditional Songs, 1969 - 1971 (Box 2)
  - Games & Crafts
    - Children's Games, 1970 - 1974 (Box 2)
    - Country Cloth, undated, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kboo, undated (Box 2)
    - Malang, 1970 - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Interviews/Surveys
    - Balama, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Benjamin-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Bunug-Ma, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Feema-Ta, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Gabai-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu-Kpai Kweli, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu-Manin Kweli, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu-Siyeta-Kweli, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu-Sulonma-Kweli, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Gumei, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Kiamu-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Kolahun History, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Kolo-Kwele, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kogo-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Kpanawei-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Kweni-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Labor Surveys, undated (Box 2)
    - Loma, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Mandingo, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Mena-Tig-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Moluba-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Gumakolii-Ta, undated (Box 2)
    - Nyaipu-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Nyyuc Yaila, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Pa lala, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Pele-Polu, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Rural Development Questionnaire, undated (Box 2)
    - Sumo-Kai-Sia-Ta, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Tokolog-Ta, undated (Box 2)
    - Tokpa-Ta, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Tulemu, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Yakpalo-Ta, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Yee-Mei, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Zagee, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Magic
    - Divination, 1967 - 1969 (Box 2)
    - Kpelle, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Possession, undated (Box 2)
    - Witchcraft, 1964 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Medicine
    - Animal Doubles, 1969 - 1972 (Box 2)
    - Birth & Survival Rates, 1973 - 1974 (Box 2)
    - Country Medicine, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Fertility, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kpelle, 1968 - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Phebe Hospital, 1970 - 1972 (Box 2)
    - Studies, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Stuffing, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Tribal Medicine, 1961 - 1971 (Box 2)
    - Twins, 1971 (Box 2)
  - People
    - African Women, undated (Box 2)
    - Balama Residents, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Cultural Heritage, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Dan/Guere or Gio/Kran, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Dey, undated (Box 2)
    - Gbansu Biographies, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Gbansu Genealogies, undated (Box 2)
    - Gbansu Residents, undated (Box 2)
    - Gbansu Surveys, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Glebo, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Goe, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kpelle Ethnic Personality, undated (Box 2)
    - Kpelle Ethnography I, 1965 - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle Ethnography II, 1965 - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle History - Christopher Dorweh, 1970 - 1974 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle History - John Korkoya, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle Life & Practice, 1965 - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle Women, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Krahn, undated (Box 3)
    - Kru, 1939 - 1977 (Box 3)
    - Kwii, 1968 - 1974 (Box 3)
    - Lofa County History, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Loma, undated (Box 3)
    - Lorma, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Madame Suakoko, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Madingo, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Meleki Residents, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Mixed, undated (Box 3)
    - Parakole, 1966 - 1968 (Box 3)
    - Sinyea History, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Sinyea Residents, 1965 - 1969 (Box 3)
    - Sucromo History, undated, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Yakpolo Family, 1965 - 1973 (Box 3)
  - Religion
    - African Religion, undated (Box 3)
    - Episcopal Church,, undated, 1960 - 2001 (Box 3)
    - Islam, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Kpelle Religion, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969 -1981 (Box 3)
    - Missionaries, undated, 1971 - 1972 (Box 3)
    - Supernatural, 1968 (Box 3)
- Economy
  - Industry
    - Business Enterprise, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Business Growth, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Case Studies, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Cooperatives undated, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Entrepreneurship, 1965 - 1975 (Box 3)
    - Iron, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Issues/Problems, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Labor Surveys, undated, 1921 - 1973 (Box 3)
    - LAMCO,, undated, 1969 - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Manpower in Upper Lofa County, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Mining, 1964 - 1969 (Box 3)
    - Rubber, 1959 - 1979 (Box 4)
    - Summaries/Surveys, 1964 - 1966 (Box 4)
    - United Nations Development Programme Assistance, 1974 (Box 4)
    - The Upper Lofa Project, undated (Box 4)
  - Minsitry of Planning & Economic Affairs
    - Censuses, 1972 - 1974 (Box 4)
    - Conferences, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Economic Development undated, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Equality, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Human & Natural Resource Development, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Institutional Planning, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Planning & Planning Machinery: Data Gathering Analysis, & Research, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Rural-Regional Development Planning, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Urban Employment Development, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Technology & Impact, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Trade
    - Agricultural Trade, undated (Box 4)
    - Coastal Trade, undated, 1970 - 1978 (Box 4)
    - Market Prices, undated, 1969 - 1972 (Box 4)
    - Merchants, 1970 - 1977 (Box 4)
    - Slave Trade/Labor, 1973 (Box 4)
- Education
  - Curriculum
    - Changes in Curriculum, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Conference, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Lectures, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Materials, 1970 (Box 4)
    - High School Curriculum, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Higher Ed Curriculum, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Educational Development
    - Educational Development in Liberia, 1964 - 1971 (Box 4)
    - Factors, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Rural School Development, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Education in Liberia
    - Education & Vocation, undated, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Education Elements, undated (Box 4)
    - Education Reform, undated (Box 4)
    - Educational Systems, undated (Box 4)
    - Educational Views, undated (Box 4)
    - Interviews, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Liberian Schools, 1959 -1967 (Box 4)
    - Notes on Education of Kpelle, 1965 - 1966 (Box 4)
    - Schools of Papers, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Higher Ed
    - African Studies, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Cuttington College, 1969 - 1972 (Box 4)
    - University of Liberia, 1971 - 1988 (Box 4)
  - Liberia
    - Elementary School Lessons, 1971 (Box 4)
    - High School Lesson Plans, undated (Box 4)
    - Kpelle Grammar, undated (Box 4)
    - Kpelle Verb Forms, undated (Box 4)
    - Missionary Lesson Plans, undated (Box 4)
    - Syllabus, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Liberian Research Association
    - Conferences, 1968 - 1972 (Box 4)
    - Membership List, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Reports, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Literacy
    - Literacy Materials, 1969 - 1971 (Box 4)
    - National Literacy Campaign, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Vai Literacy Project, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Problems
    - Causes of & Solutions to Issues in Education, 1969 - 1973 (Box 5)
    - Dropouts, 1970 - 1972 (Box 5)
    - Economic Effects on Education, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Improved Efficiency of Learning Project, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Mass Education, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Sande School Closing Photos, 1967 (Box 5)
    - School Closings, 1965 - 1967 (Box 5)
    - Unification, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Psychology
    - Cognition, undated, 1965 - 1972 (Box 5)
    - Communication, undated, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Cultural Difference Theory, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Decision-Making, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Language & Behavior, undated (Box 5)
    - Logic, undated, 1964 - 1973 (Box 5)
    - Quantitative Behavior, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Social Roles, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Studies & Experiments, undated (Box 5)
    - Traditional Politics, undated (Box 5)
  - School Types
    - Bush Schools, undated, 1965 - 1967 (Box 5)
    - Comparisons, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Government Schools, 1969 (Box 5)
    - High Schools, undated, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Religious Schools, undated, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Teachers
    - National Teachers Association of Liberia,, undated, 1960 - 1962 (Box 5)
    - Research & Studies, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Rules & Regulations, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Teacher Training Workshops, 1966 - 1990 (Box 5)
    - Teaching Roles, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Zorzor Teacher Training Institute, 1968 (Box 5)
- Government
  - Americo-Liberians
    - Americo-Liberian Oligarchy, 1969 - 1989 (Box 5)
    - Settlers, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Tolbert, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Tubman Era, 1971 - 1977 (Box 5)
  - Civil Conflicts
    - African Magazine Articles, 1979 - 1990 (Box 5)
    - American Magazine Articles, 1980 - 1998 (Box 5)
    - Bulletins undated, 1984 - 1989 (Box 5)
    - Child Soldiers, undated (Box 5)
    - Clippings - Unknown Source, undated (Box 5)
    - Complete Magazines, 1981 - 1990 (Box 5)
    - Cows of Dolo Ken Paye, undated (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, Bantu-Zangai, 1980 - 2002 (Box 5)
    - The Daily Observer Clippings, 1988 (Box 5)
    - ECOWAS/ECOMOG, 1992 (Box 5)
    - European Magazine Articles, undated (Box 5)
    - Foreign Involvement, undated (Box 5)
    - Friends of Liberia,, undated, 1992 - 1995 (Box 5)
    - Humanitarian Appeals, 1990 - 1998 (Box 5)
    - International Herald Tribune,, undated, 1980 - 1990 (Box 5)
    - Kpelle Warfare, 1919 - 1972 (Box 5)
    - Liberia After the Coup, undated (Box 5)
    - Liberia National Transitional Government, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Liberia Update, 1988 - 1990 (Box 6)
    - Liberia Watch, 1989 - 1991 (Box 6)
    - Liberian Frontier Force, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Mani Invasions, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Magazine Articles, 1979 - 1998 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Newspaper & Clippings, 1980 - 1988 (Box 6)
    - New York Times & New York Post Clippings,, undated, 1980 - 1988 (Box 6)
    - Programs, Pamphlets, Speeches, 1980 - 1989 (Box 6)
    - Social Conditions, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Solutions, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Washington Post & Washington Times,, undated, 1980 - 1989 (Box 6)
  - Foreign Policy
    - Liberian Diplomatic Relations, undated (Box 6)
    - Policy During World Wars, undated (Box 6)
    - United States Policy & its Influence, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Government Practices
    - Colonialism, undated, 1858 - 1974 (Box 6)
    - Continuity, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Decentralization, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Debt, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Detribalization, undated (Box 6)
    - History, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Hut Tax, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Imperialism, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Ministry of Information, Cultural Affairs, & Tourism, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Modernization, undated (Box 6)
    - Nationalism, undated, 1971 - 1972 (Box 6)
    - Regulations, 1931 (Box 6)
    - Taxation, undated (Box 6)
    - Westernization, undated (Box 6)
  - History
    - Emergence of the Nation, undated (Box 6)
    - Exploration, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Migration, undated, 1970 - 1974 (Box 6)
    - The Scramble for Africa undated (Box 6)
  - Law
    - Arson Case, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Assassination of Bishop Brown,, undated, 1969 - 1970 (Box 6)
    - Bellemu Case, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Case of the Sojourning Wife, undated, 1965 - 1968 (Box 6)
    - Complaints, 1965 (Box 6)
    - House Palaver Cases, 1965 (Box 6)
    - J.P. Case, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Kpelle Law, undated, 1963 - 1971 (Box 6)
    - Marriage Cases, undated (Box 6)
    - Personal Accounts, 1966 - 1974 (Box 6)
    - School Palavers, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Trials, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Maps & Geography
    - Archaeology, 1967 - 1974 (Box 6)
    - Bureau of Natural Resources & Surveys, 1966 - 1967 (Box 6)
    - Department of Defense Maps, 1966 - 1969 (Box 6)
    - Geology, undated (Box 6)
    - Geophysics, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Liberian Geographic Names, 1955 (Box 6)
    - Liberian Geography, undated, 1953 - 1969 (Box 6)
    - Liberian Maps, undated, 1952 - 1972 (Box 6)
    - Maps of Gbansu Area, 1973 - 1974 (Box 6)
    - Mineral Resources, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Invitations/Greeting Cards, 1960 - 1972 (Box 7)
    - Open Letter to Attorney General, 1967 (Box 7)
    - Programs, 1959 - 1972 (Box 7)
  - Political Systems
    - Agenda - National Patriotic front, 1990 (Box 7)
    - Chiefdoms, undated, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Family & Political Class Structure, 1974 (Box 7)
    - Kpelle Interviews, 1960 (Box 7)
    - Kpelle Politics, undated, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Kpliopo & Wedabo Politics, undated (Box 7)
  - Transportation
    - CARE/Sierra Leone Rural Penetration Roads, undated (Box 7)
    - Traffic Density Surveys, 1970 (Box 7)
- Linguistics
  - Kpelle
    - Categorization, undated (Box 7)
    - Class, Identification, undated (Box 7)
    - Classification, 1965 - 1973 (Box 7)
    - Fieldwork, undated, 1964 (Box 7)
    - Grammatical Outline, undated (Box 7)
    - Kaaseg, undated, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Kinship terms, 1967 - 1974 (Box 7)
    - Nominals, undated, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Phonology, undated, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Syntax, undated (Box 7)
    - Verbal System, undated (Box 7)
    - Wm. E. Welmers Grammar Research, 1964 - 1972 (Box 7)
    - Word Lists, undated (Box 7)
  - Languages
    - Gola, 1962 (Box 7)
    - Krahn, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Kru, undated, 1972 - 1977 (Box 7)
    - Languages of Liberia - Overview,, undated, 1970 (Box 7)
    - Liberian English, undated, 1962 - 1972 (Box 7)
    - Linguistics Programs, undated, 1971 - 1973 (Box 7)
    - Loma, undated (Box 7)
    - Mande, undated (Box 7)
    - Mel, 1965 (Box 7)
    - Vai, undated, 1967 - 1978 (Box 7)
  - Proverbs
    - Collected by John Korkoyah, 1967 - 1969 (Box 7)
    - Collected by Paul Ricks, 1972 (Box 7)
    - Collected by William Murphy,, undated, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Use & Interpretation Among Kpelle, 1970 - 1973 (Box 7)
- Publications
  - Arts & Literature
    - Education for the Masses, Selected Poetic Works Neville Best, undated (Box 8)
    - Essay and Poems E.K. Sherman, undated (Box 8)
    - Liberian Arts and Crafts, undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Literature, undated, 1963 - 1979 (Box 8)
  - Bibliographical References
    - Bibliography of Foreign Languages, Frances Ingemann, undated (Box 8)
    - Biography on Liberia, (Parts I-III)" Svend Holsoe, 1971 - 1976 (Box 8)
    - General Bibliography of the Republic of Liberia Warren D'Azevedo & Marvin Solomon, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Liberia in the 19th Century: a Bibliographic Essay, Harry Moribs, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous References, undated (Box 8)
    - Study Guide for Liberia, Svend Holsoe, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Educational Materials
    - Improved Efficiency of Learning Workbooks, undated, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Kpelle Language Workbooks, undated (Box 8)
      General
      3 Folders
    - Mathematics and Logic in the Kpelle Language, John Gay & William Wellmers, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Articles, undated, 1970 - 1984 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Educational Booklets, undated, 1962 - 1980 (Box 8)
    - New Directions for Education and Training in Liberia, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Socio-Economic Characteristics of Candidates for the Liberian National Examination, Bertha Azango, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Foreign Language
    - Liberia, Dick Manfred, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Book Chapter in French P. Lassort & M. H. Lelong, 1947 (Box 8)
    - Loma Weekly Paper, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Religious Stories, 1963 - 1966 (Box 8)
    - Fables, Stories, and Workbooks, undated, 1957 - 1966 (Box 8)
  - Journals
    - Journals, 1971 - 1999 (Box 9)
    - Liberia Forum, 1986 - 1988 (Box 9)
    - Liberian Studies, 1967 (Box 9)
    - Liberian Historical Review, 1964 - 1971 (Box 9)
    - Letter to the Liberian Research Association, Bertha Baker Azango, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Liberian Research Association Journal, 1968 - 1972 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Addresses Given by William R. Tolbert, Jr., 1971 - 1973 (Box 9)
    - Calendars, 1980 - 1981 (Box 9)
    - Conference Proram, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Directory and Who's Who, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Handbook for Lutherans in Liberia, undated (Box 9)
    - Liberia Watch, undated (Box 10)
    - Kpelle - English Dictionary, Pt. 1 Theodore Leidenfrost & John S. McKay, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Kpelle Literacy Center Calendars, 1974 - 1980 (Box 10)
    - Letters between Dr. Werner Korte & John Gay, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Liberia Working Group, Papers and Publications Order Forms, 1989 (Box 10)